哇，这一年真是不得了。
Well, what a year that was.
2025年对建筑业来说是个大年。
2025 was huge for construction.
我们见证了各种工程的兴建与倒塌，
We've seen things go up, things come down,
几乎什么状况都发生过。
and pretty much everything happen in between.
这是因为行业里成千上万技术精湛、勤劳肯干的人
It's because thousands of skilled, hardworking people in this industry
每天都在用双手塑造我们的世界，
get up every day to shape our world
看起来轻描淡写，
and kind of make it look easy,
但其实一点都不简单。
but it's not.
有时候，事情就是会出岔子。
Sometimes things can go wrong.
我们一向喜欢聊这个行业里那些了不起的事情。
And look, we love talking about what makes this industry great.
所以我们并不是要小题大做，
So, it's not that we want to make a big deal out of it,
但年底了嘛，
but it's the end of the year
大家都爱看年终盘点视频。
and everyone loves a big roundup video.
那就来看看2025年十大建筑工程灾难。
So, here are the 10 biggest construction disasters of 2025.
首先，你可能还记得这件事。
First up, you may remember this.
>> 这是九月份那惊心动魄的一幕——
>> It was the dramatic moment in September
曼谷街头突然裂开一个巨大的天坑。
when a huge sinkhole tore open a street in Bangkok.
在地下40米深处，
40 m beneath the surface,
曼谷地铁紫线新延伸段的施工工作正在推进。
work was progressing on this,
a new extension to the Bangkok Metro's Purple Line.
这里就是新建的瓦吉拉医院站的位置。
Here's the location of the new Vajira Hospital Station.
问题出在隧道与站厅
The problem started when work connecting the tunnel to the station hall
连接施工时，顶板被打穿，
ruptured the ceiling,
导致隧道发生坍塌。
causing the tunnel to collapse.
最早的异常迹象出现在清晨，
The first clue something was wrong came early in the morning
地面开始涌水。
when water was seen welling up on the road.
随后，早上7点13分，这一幕发生了。
Then, at 7:13 a.m., this happened.
一个深达50米的巨型天坑骤然裂开，
A massive 50 m deep sinkhole opened up
大到足以将比萨斜塔整个吞进去。
large enough to swallow the leaning tower of Pisa.
更糟糕的是，
And if that wasn't bad enough,
这个车站叫什么名字来着？
what was the name of that station again?
没错。
That's right.
天坑就在这里裂开。
This is where the sinkhole opened up.
而这里是瓦吉拉医院，
And this is Vajara Hospital,
每年接诊住院病人约三万名，门诊病人约七十万名。
home to around 30,000 inatients and 700,000 outpatients every year.
医院随即紧急疏散。
The hospital was immediately evacuated.
所幸没有人员伤亡。
And fortunately, there were no casualties.
隧道施工随即全面暂停，目前尚未复工。
Work on the tunnel was paused immediately and is yet to continue.
从统计数据来看，看这个视频的大多数人是美国人。
Now, statistically, most of you watching this video are American.
不过，还是有一些人可能认识这个地方。
But still, a few of you may recognize this.
老特拉福德，曼彻斯特联队的主场，
Old Trafford, home to Manchester United,
世界上最伟大的足球俱乐部之一。
one of the greatest football teams in the world.
至少在他们传奇主帅2013年退休之前是这样的。
Or at least they were until their legendary manager retired in 2013.
自那以后，他们的状态就一直不太行了。
And they've kind of been rubbish ever since.
于是，像所有球队在成绩下滑时
So, like any club would do when their team is underperforming,
都会做的那样，
they decided to build
他们决定斥资建一座全新的豪华大球场。
a huge brand new multi-million dollar stadium.
英国最著名的足球俱乐部
Britain's most famous football club
找来了英国最著名的建筑师——
turned to Britain's most famous architect
那位穿紫色西装
and the coolest guy you've ever seen in a purple suit,
帅得令人叹为观止的诺曼·福斯特。
Norman Foster.
他拿出的方案是这样的：
This is what he came up with.
一座可容纳十万名观众的超大球场，覆盖在一个巨型遮篷之下，
A vast 100,000 seat stadium sheltered under a huge umbrella
能够收集阳光和雨水。
capable of harvesting sunlight and rainwater.
方案大气磅礴、标志性十足，
It was a bold iconic structure
看起来活像一顶巨型马戏团帐篷。
and it looked like a huge circus tent.
曼彻斯特人和英国那些出了名刻薄的媒体没多久就注意到了这一点。
It didn't take long for Manunians or Britain's notoriously savage press to notice.
再加上球队近期的糟糕表现，各种标题简直是自己送上门来的。
Add to that the team's recent performance and the headlines kind of wrote themselves.
就在方案公布仅仅7个月后的
In October, just 7 months after plans were announced,
十月，新球场的消息被悄悄确认：
it was quietly confirmed
球场依然会建，
the new stadium would still be going ahead,
但那顶"大帐篷"没了。
but without the big top.
>> 好了。
>> That's it.
你们这些人拦了我太久了。
You people have stood in my way long enough.
我要去克隆大学了。
I'm going to clone college.
>> 我想谁都没料到他会说出这话。
>> I don't think any of us expected him to say that.
>> 曼彻斯特在叫停过于雄心勃勃的项目这方面，根本不算什么顶级水平。
>> Manchester is nowhere near the Premier League of scrapping overly ambitious projects.
要看真正的大手笔，我们得去沙特阿拉伯。
For that, we need to head to Saudi Arabia.
三年前，这个国家宣布要在沙漠中建造一座170公里长的直线城市，
It's been 3 years since this country stunned the world by announcing the Line,
震惊了全世界。
a 170 km linear city in the desert.
然后，还没等人说完"根本建不了"，
Then, faster than you can say unbuildable,
一大批所谓的超级工程就相继亮相。
a slew of other so-called giga products were unveiled.
其中很多位于沙特新规划区域NEOM之内。
many of them in the country's new region of Neo.
当然，所有人都说这根本不可能实现。
Obviously, everyone said it could never be done.
对此，沙特阿拉伯的回应是——
To which Saudi Arabia replied,
"嗯，不完全是，但差不多。"
"Well, not quite, but kind of."
然后，仿佛这还不够，他们甚至真的开始动工了。
Then, as if that wasn't enough, they even started building it.
沙漠中出现了巨大的壕沟、
There was a huge trench in the desert,
数不清的打桩机和大量混凝土，
endless piling rigs, oceans of concrete,
然后 >> 沙特阿拉伯已要求咨询公司
and then >> Saudi Arabia has asked consulting firms
对NEOM开发项目直线城市的建设计划进行战略审查。
to conduct a strategic review of its plans for building Neon's development project, The Line.
>> 是的，2025年对NEOM来说是艰难的一年。
>> Yeah, 2025 has been a rough year for Neome.
据《金融时报》报道，
According to the Financial Times,
几乎所有NEOM项目的施工都陷入停滞，
work has grown to a halt on almost all NEOM projects,
而直线城市——
and the line is, wait for it,
做好心理准备——已经超支了数万亿美元。
trillions of dollars over budget.
目前据说仍获全力支持的
One project that apparently retains full backing
项目是特罗耶纳，
is Traina,
一个计划在沙漠山地建造的滑雪度假村和人工湖。
a ski resort and artificial lake in the desert mountains.
它计划承办2029年亚洲冬季运动会，
It's due to host the 2029 Asian Winter Games,
但现在买票可能还是先缓一缓。
but maybe hold off buying a ticket just yet.
十月份，距开幕式不到四年，
In October, with less than 4 years to go before the opening ceremony,
NEOM居然
it turned out Neom
还在找人来负责建造这个项目。
was still looking for someone to build it.
有句话说得好：深陷泥潭，就该停止继续挖坑。
You could say that once you're in a hole, you really should stop digging.
这恰好完美地引出了我们的下一个项目。
Which brings us very nicely onto our next project.
这是斯诺维水电工程，澳大利亚东南部一个庞大的水力发电站网络。
This is Snowy Hydro, a vast network of hydroelectric power plants in Southeast Australia.
它是澳大利亚有史以来规模最大的工程项目，也是一项了不起的成就。
It's the biggest engineering project ever undertaken in the country and an extraordinary achievement.
这是斯诺维2号工程，
This is Snowy 2,
一个旨在连接原有两座水库
a successor project designed to connect two of the original reservoirs
并新建一座发电站的后续项目。
and create a new power plant.
而这位是弗洛伦斯，
And this is Florence,
那台在开工短短几周后就
the tunnel boring machine
卡住了的隧道掘进机（盾构机）。
that got stuck just weeks after it started work.
说实话，在那之前事情就已经不太顺利了，
To be fair, things weren't exactly going well before that happened,
但这一事故导致
but that contributed to a cost blowout
预算在短短6个月内翻了一番，
that saw the budget double
飙升至近80亿美元。
to nearly $8 billion US in just 6 months.
卡机的原因是弗洛伦斯遭遇了出乎意料的松软地层。
The sticky situation was caused by Florence running into unexpectedly soft ground.
正如首席执行官丹尼斯·巴恩斯所说：
As chief executive Dennis Barnes put it,
我们根本不知道地质条件会这么差，显然确实如此。
we just didn't know it was that soft, clearly.
不过那都是2024年的事了。
But that was back in 2024.
那之后又发生了什么？嗯，
So, what's been happening since? Well,
经过大量努力，弗洛伦斯终于脱困，
after a lot of effort, Florence eventually got unstuck
施工得以继续，
and work continued,
至少持续了一段时间。
at least for a little bit.
一月份，
Things stopped again in January
由于避难室未经妥善
due to concerns that refuge chambers
维护，施工再度叫停。
hadn't been properly maintained.
那些避难室是在
Those are the areas
隧道发生塌陷时工人
that workers are supposed to take shelter
应当躲避的紧急避险区域。
in if the tunnel starts to collapse.
不仅如此，十月份还下令对整个项目进行逐条逐项的审计，
Not only that, but in October, a line by line audit was ordered of the entire project.
预计需要9个月，
It's expected to take 9 months
而且——剧透一下——费用不会少。
and spoiler alert, it's not going to be cheap.
但这与乌克兰那边发生的毁灭性事件相比，就显得微不足道了。
But that pales in comparison with a devastating development over in Ukraine.
今年早些时候，我们报道了一条令人震惊的消息：切尔诺贝利
Earlier this year, we covered the breathtaking news that Chernobyl
>> 3.6，不算好，也不算糟。
>> 3.6. Not great, not terrible.
>> 对，就是那里，遭到了无人机袭击。
>> Yeah, that one had been struck in a drone attack.
袭击发生在2月14日凌晨2点，
The strike happened at 2:00 a.m. on the 14th of February,
俄制"柳叶刀"无人机的
and the remains of the Russian Danto drone
残骸在废墟中被找到。
were found in the wreckage.
这次袭击在密封覆盖着臭名昭著的
The attack blasted a 6 m wide hole
4号反应堆的保护罩上炸开了一个6米宽的洞。
in the hermetically sealed shelter
covering the infamous reactor 4.
更糟糕的是，爆炸引燃了保护罩的外覆层，
What's worse, the blast ignited the shield's cladding,
导致火势
causing a fire to spread internally
在屋顶内部蔓延。
throughout the roof.
大火燃烧了数周才被扑灭。
A fire which took several weeks to extinguish.
我们应该有多担心呢？
So, how worried should we be?
目前没有直接危险，
Well, it's important to note there's no immediate danger,
这一点很重要。但如果
but that could change if parts or all
内部老化的反应堆结构开始局部或全面坍塌，情况可能随时改变。
of the aging reactor structure inside began to collapse.
目前正在着手设计屋顶修补方案，
Work is underway on designing a patch for the roof,
但从长远来看，
but in the long run,
这个保护罩很可能永远无法得到彻底修复。
it looks unlikely the shield can never be fully repaired.
>> 嘿，听我说。
>> Hell, listen to me.
>> 今年早些时候，大使凯特·怀勒又回到了我们的视野，
>> Earlier this year, Ambassador Kate Wiler returns to our screens
出现在我们频道介绍过的那座豪华使馆大楼里，
in the very fancy embassy building, which we featured on the channel,
不过她并不是城里唯一一位风头正劲的大使。
but she's not the only hot shot ambassador in town.
这里可能就是
This may or may not be the site
中国驻英新使馆的选址，也可能不是。
of the new Chinese embassy in the United Kingdom.
如果一切按计划进行，现在应该已经建好了。
Now, had all gone to plan, it would probably be built by now.
但这个故事的剧情反转之多，
But this saga has had so many plot twists
连怀勒大使
that even Ambassador Wiler
都未必跟得上。
wouldn't be able to keep up.
>> 哈尔，你干了什么？
>> Hal, what did you do?
>> 我不知道哈尔有没有参与其中，
>> Well, I don't know if Hal was involved,
不过这就是你们第二季的节目——
but this is your season 2 roundup
驻外大使之中国使馆版。
of the diplomat Chinese embassy edition.
2021年，中国希望在伦敦建造一座新使馆，
Back in 2021, China wanted to build a new embassy in London,
但官员对建筑图纸中
but officials were concerned about gigantic
一个巨大的无标注地下室感到疑虑。
unmarked basement on the plants.
中国郑重承诺绝不将其用于间谍活动，
China absolutely promised not to use it for spying,
但规划许可
but still planned permission was denied
还是以安全为由被拒绝了。
on security grounds.
后来英国举行了大选，
But then Britain had an election
新政府对中国的态度友好得多。
and the new government was a lot friendlier to China.
>> 哦，老朋友。
>> Oh friend.
>> 于是中国重新提交了方案，
>> So China resubmissed its plans
负责审批的政府部长承诺亲自监督这份申请。
and the government minister responsible promised to oversee the application personally.
所有人都以为她会放行，
Everyone assumed she would greenlight it,
但就在她宣布决定的一个月前，
but a month before she announced her decision,
她因丑闻辞职了。
she resigned over a scandal.
此后，英国情报首长
After that, Britain spy chiefs sounded the alarm
就中国特工通过领英（LinkedIn）招募英国议员一事发出警告，
over Chinese spies recruiting British MPs over LinkedIn,
使馆项目再度看起来前途渺茫。
and the embassy once again looked doomed.
直到十一月，
Until in November,
有消息泄露称英国首相卡玛 67
it was leaked that Prime Minister Karma 67
>> 预计将批准建设。[倒吸冷气和叹息声]
>> was expected to approve the build. [gasps and sighs]
截至本视频发布时，尚无任何官方公告，
At the time of this video publishing, there's not been any official announcement,
也不清楚是否
and it's unclear if a deadline
设定了决策截止日期，
for a decision has been set,
这意味着等这个视频出来的时候，
which could mean that by the time this video comes out,
整件事可能已经获批并建好了，
the whole thing could have been approved and built,
也可能没有，谁知道呢？
or not, maybe. Who knows?
鱼的价格
What has the price of fish
和英国最新的核电站有什么关系？
got to do with Britain's newest nuclear power station?
这是欣克利角C核电站，
This is Hinckley Point C,
一座能够满足
a vast new facility capable of churning
英国7%电力需求的大型发电设施。
out 7% of the UK's electricity needs.
只不过英国已经三十年没建过类似的项目了，
Only Britain hasn't built anything like it in 30 years
多少有些生疏。
and has gotten a little bit rusty.
项目受到劳动力和材料短缺的
The bill's been played by labor and material shortages
拖累，加上新冠疫情和英国脱欧
and disruption caused by co and Brexit
带来的冲击，总造价已飙升至480亿英镑，
has sent the bill soaring to 48 billion pounds
可能成为史上造价最高的核电站。
making it potentially the most expensive nuclear power plant in history.
此外还有一个更大的问题：鲑鱼。
Plus, there's an even bigger issue. Salmon.
十一月，一份政府报告披露，
In November, a government report discovered the plans
该选址的计划中包含
for the site included
一套耗资7亿英镑的声学驱鱼装置，
a 700 million pound acoustic deterrent
用于保护当地海洋生物。
aimed at protecting local marine life.
英国媒体再次大做文章，
Once again, the British press had a bit of a field day,
尤其是当这套所谓的"鱼类迪斯科"
especially when the so-called fish disco
据估计每12年才能救下一条鲑鱼时。
was only estimated to save one salmon every 12 years.
这代价可真不小。
That's a big go.
接下来看德国。
Over to Germany now,
凭借其工程实力和德意志技术精神，
and with its engineering prowess and voron dur technic,
这应该是一个基础设施非常完善的国家，
it's one country that you'd expect to have really good infrastructure,
对吧？
right?
嗯，[哼笑一声] 才怪。
Well, [snorts] wrong.
德国铁路系统的糟糕状况早在2024年欧洲杯期间就彻底暴露了。
The state of Germany's railways crashed onto the scene
back in 2024 during the Euros.
没有一班火车准时到达。
Not a single train has been on time.
>> 但火车还是不走。
>> But the train won't move.
我们遭遇了第一次延误。
We're hit with our first delay.
>> 德国效率真是令人大失所望。
>> German efficiency is very disappointing.
德国铁路系统已经乱了一段时间，
Germany's rail system has been a mess for a while,
但各方正在努力将其升级到
but efforts are being made to upgrade it
至少能正常运转的水平。
to something at least functional.
其中的旗舰项目就是斯图加特21工程，计划很简单：
The flagship project is this Stutgart 21. The plan is simple.
将该市的主要终点站改造成贯通式车站，
Turn the city's main terminus into a through station
并将其升级为区域交通枢纽。
and transform it into a regional hub.
不用说，事情并没有那么简单。
Needless to say, it's not been as simple as that.
其中一个主要问题是隧道内轨道的坡度。
One major problem has been the gradient of the tracks in the tunnels.
规定允许的最大坡度为0.25%。
The maximum regulations allow for is 0.25%.
但斯图加特隧道内的坡度达到了1.51%，
But the tunnels in Stokart are laid to 1.51%
这意味着列车有可能在停站后
which means trains could start rolling away from the platform
因自身惯性而自行滑动。
under their own momentum.
最近又出现了新信号系统方面的问题，
More recently, problems have emerged with the new signaling system
该系统本是为了取代传统信号灯而设计的。
that's designed to phase out old-fashioned lights.
细节尚不明朗，但一系列风险已经浮现，
Details are light, but a series of risks have emerged
整个升级项目目前陷入停摆。
and the whole upgrade is stuck on red.
万一你收到了2026年竣工庆典的邀请，
And in case you were invited to the grand opening party in 2026,
很遗憾，那个派对已经取消了。
it's unfortunately been cancelled.
德国在工程建设上或许举步维艰，
While Germany might be struggling with engineering,
而美国一个标志性铁路项目的停滞
one of America's flagship rail projects is being held up
则是另有原因。
for a very different reason.
加州高速铁路自2015年破土动工以来，
California highspeed rail has been plagued by delays and cost blowouts
一直深陷延误和超支的泥潭。
since it broke ground back in 2015.
事实证明，在全国地价最贵的地区之一征地，
It turns out that buying land in one of the most expensive parts
确实要花不少钱。
of the country costs quite a bit of money.
众所周知，特朗普总统从来就不支持这个项目。
Now, President Trump has never been a fan of this project.
他在第一任期内曾试图撤资，
He tried to pull funding during his first term,
然后在2025年7月再度出手，
and then in July 2025, he tried again,
声称要追回逾450亿美元的联邦拨款。
claiming back over 45 billion US in federal funding.
此事目前正在法院提出挑战，短期内看不到解决的希望。
That's being challenged in the courts, and a resolution isn't expected anytime soon.
但这并不是美国唯一一个
But it's not the only infrastructure project in the US
陷入资金困境的基础设施项目。
that's been strapped for cash.
十月份创纪录的政府关门，对全国各地的项目造成了严重冲击。
The record-breaking government shutdown in October, played havoc with projects right across the country.
受冲击最严重的是纽约的哈德逊隧道门户项目，
The worst hit was New York's Hudson tunnel gateway program,
这毫无疑问是全美最关键的
easily one of the most critical tunnel schemes
隧道工程之一。
in the entire country.
180亿美元的联邦拨款遭到冻结，
$18 billion in federal funding, was frozen,
特朗普甚至宣称他已终止该项目。
and Donald Trump even declared he had terminated the project.
接下来走向如何，谁也说不准。
Where we go from here is anyone's guess.
说到灾难性的铁路项目，
We couldn't talk about disastrous rail projects without also mentioning
怎么能不提那个老面孔——英国HS2高铁。
that old favorite Britain's highspeed 2.
这个国家或许在200年前发明了铁路，
The country may have invented the railways 200 years ago,
但自那以后就一直没太顺过。
but it's not gone very well since.
从哪里说起HS2呢？
Where to start with HS2?
嗯，这本身就是问题的一部分。
Well, that's partly the problem.
这条命运多舛的线路原本计划将伦敦
The ill- fated line was meant to link London
与英格兰北部多个城市相连。
with several destinations in the north of England.
2020年，施工从伦敦率先启动。
So, in 2020, construction began in London.
悲观者会说，他们之所以只从伦敦开始，
Now, a cynic would say that they only started in London
是因为这个项目从一开始就不得人心，
because the project was highly unpopular from the start
英国政府这样一来就不必全面承诺建设整个路网，
and the UK government wouldn't have to fully commit to building the entire network
一旦哪段线路引发争议，
and could scrap parts of it
随时可以砍掉。
if the route ever got too controversial.
当然啦，那种事绝对不会发生。
But of course, that would never happen.
尽管，那恰恰就是实际发生的事。
Although, that's literally exactly what happened.
时至今日，HS2缩短了335公里，
Today, HS2 is 335 km shorter,
多花了680亿英镑，
68 billion pounds more expensive,
而且没人真正知道它什么时候能建完。
and no one really knows when it's going to be finished.
那有什么新进展呢？
So, what's new?
嗯，十月份有消息宣布，一段29公里的区间
Well, in October, it was announced that a 29 km section
——用于将HS2与主干铁路网络连接——
linking HS2 to the rest of the mainline network
被列为"非优先"，意味着至少还要再等4年才能完工。
was being depprioritized, meaning it won't be finished for another 4 years.
但走到这一步，还有谁在认真计数呢？
But at this stage, who's even still counting?
好了，就是这些。
So, there you have it.
2025年十大建筑工程失败案例，
The 10 biggest construction fails of 2025,
我们没来得及聊阿康在萨迦尔的新城项目——
and we ran out of time to talk about Acon's new city in Sagal,
那个已经被正式叫停了。
which was officially scrapped.
如果你已经看够了失败案例，
Now, if you've had enough Shard and Freder and want to see
想在2026年见识一些真正令人叹服的超级工程，
some truly impressive mega projects in 26,
别担心，我们帮你搞定。
don't worry because we've got your back.
记得订阅B1M频道，
Make sure you subscribe to the B1M
让这些精彩内容持续出现在你的推送里。
to keep all this great stuff coming into your feed.
别忘了，我们正在通过投资Brick Borrow来激励下一代建造者——
Don't forget guys that we're inspiring the next generation of builders
那是一个超棒的乐高订阅服务。
through our investment into Brick Borrow, a fantastic LEGO subscription service.
想了解更多或立即开始，请访问brickbarrow.com。
You can learn more and get started today over at brickbarrow.com.
一如既往，如果你喜欢这个视频，
And as always guys, if you enjoyed this video
想获取更多来自这个权威建筑视频频道的内容，
and you want to get more from the definitive video channel for construction,
记得订阅B1M频道。
make sure you're subscribed to the B1M.